[BURTON] Our son's fever
isn't coming down!
And he's having trouble
breathing!
If this keeps up, I don't
think-- Please, I beg you!
Help my boy!
[LORD BELFOR] Quiet down,
Burton. What's the fuss?
It's my son, your lordship!
His fever is getting worse!
[LORD BELFOR]
Then you should take him
to the village
doctor immediately.
[BURTON]
We would,
but, you see, your lordship,
he's not in tonight.
He's away at his
daughter's wedding.
All we need is a moment
of your doctor's time.
[LORD BELFOR] It is
simply out of the question.
Expecting my personal physician
to attend to your ailing child.
But if nothing's done,
my boy's likely to die!
[LORD BELFOR]
So what if he does?
I don't see how
it's any of my concern
what happens to
the lower classes.
You think you're entitled
special treatment?
Let me be clear.
I employ you based solely on
your skills as a gardener.
However, bother me with
trivial matters again,
and I will replace you.
Your lordship!
If nothing's done, he'll--
[gasps]
[grunts]
[WILLIAM]
Beg your pardon,
but could I trouble you for
directions to Goetsbeck Manor?
[SUZANNA]
Goetsbeck Manor? Let me guess.
You wouldn't be that university
professor now, would you?
[WILLIAM]
Yes, but how did you know that?
[SUZANNA] You're not
in the city anymore, lad.
Out here, word travels faster
than the carriage ride over.
[SUZANNA] Not to mention,
you come from noble stock,
yet you still teach at a school.
It would've been peculiar
not hearing about you!
It would? I suppose so.
[MICHELLE grunts]
You'll have to forgive that one.
She's not fond of aristocrats.
Poor, Michelle. Can't say
I really blame her either.
Not after that business
with the Viscount.
The man basically
stood by and watched
as her son lay
dying in her arms.
[WILLIAM grunts]
Oh! You're back.
Take the scenic route?
I decided to explore
the city streets
and ended up getting
turned around.
Sounds like quite an ordeal.
Since you're back,
care for some tea?
I'll go and prepare some.
[WILLIAM]
Mm.
It feels good to be officially
settled in one's home.
I'm not sure I would
refer to this place as "home."
Other than the quick inspection
we made before purchasing it,
this is your first time
staying at the house.
True, this residence
is temporary
and was chosen based on how
close it is to the university.
But location is irrelevant.
Anywhere that I'm able to drink
your tea... I'll call my home.
[LOUIS grunts]
Oh. That reminds me.
This came for you earlier.
From the Viscount of Belfor?
[LOUIS]
Yes.
Apparently, he's the lord
over this entire region.
[WILLIAM] How neighborly.
We've only just arrived
and he's already
extending a welcoming hand.
Remind me, Louis. Is Albert
still due to arrive tonight?
He is. He said he would pay a
visit to see how everything was
after he finished
his current job.
I see.
Hope the Viscount doesn't mind
if I bring two guests.
[LORD BELFOR chewing] Mm!
I must say, this is a delight!
Cheers! To you
and your two brothers!
Having you at my table
is a true honor!
As fellow noblemen,
I hope we can enjoy each other's
company for many years to come.
As do we, your lordship.
[LORD BELFOR] What an evening!
Positively smashing!
More? We're celebrating! Mm.
Your lordship,
I think that's enough.
Ugh. Very well.
[BUTLER 04A]
It's nearly time for your dosage
of medicine as well.
Have you been feeling ill?
[LORD BELFOR] It's nothing.
Just a spot of heart trouble.
Sounds serious.
Please. There's no
cause for any alarm
as long as I have this bottle.
What's inside?
This elixir goes
by the name quinine.
It was originally a
treatment used for malaria.
But my personal physician
says it's also effective for
combating certain
heart ailments.
Huh.
[LORD BELFOR]
It might interest you to know
this quinine is
actually homemade.
The main ingredient derives
from the quina plant,
which I happen to grow here,
in my conservatory.
I take it horticulture's
one of your interests?
Ah. Well, yes. Though,
I'm honestly more interested
in the collecting aspect.
How fortunate.
Seems this hobby of yours
has yielded unexpected benefits.
Huh. You know, my
collection's quite vast.
After we finish dinner,
would you all care to
view the conservatory?
Yes. By all means.
Are you impressed?
This truly is a sight to behold.
[LORD BELFOR chuckles]
Note the variety of specimens.
Each one requires a specific
habitat and growing method.
Otherwise, it wouldn't thrive.
They do, however,
have something in common.
All of these plants are rare,
only able to spring forth
from an exceptional seed.
Quite similar to people.
Wouldn't you agree, gentlemen?
So many. I imagine
caring for them all
must be a rather
time-consuming endeavor.
Certainly, but I have
an exceptional gardener
overseeing their upkeep.
Speaking of,
there goes the man now.
Everything you see here
is tended to by him.
Name's Burton and while he's
not a very considerate chap,
there's no denying he has a gift
when it comes to plants.
From the sweat of
the lower class,
the noble stock is
able to fully bloom.
You might even say
this conservatory is
a microcosm of our society!
[LORD BELFOR laughing]
Listen, I just had a thought.
Why don't we have a
tea party in here sometime?
It'll be as though we died
and went to paradise.
[LORD BELFOR laughs]
Uh...
Do you mind explaining?
No one else lives here
besides you and me.
So why did you set three places?
[MICHELLE]
It felt right. I had a dream.
Our boy was crying
because he was hungry.
[BURTON'S SON laughing]
Tell me, what's the point
of carrying on like this?
It won't change the past!
[MICHELLE]
You're right.
It won't change what
happened that night.
Or bring him back.
In light of this
being our first class,
how about we end things
here for the day?
An excellent lecture
and easy to follow.
Indeed.
Hard to believe it was delivered
by a professor so young.
[LUCIAN]
Frankly, I'm astounded.
[TATE] Without a doubt,
he's some kind of genius.
[WILLIAM]
Would you mind if I joined you?
[BURTON grunts]
Guess that depends--who're you?
William James Moriarty,
at your service.
I recently moved to your town
to teach mathematics
at the university.
Yeah, I heard about you.
Why would a bigwig professor
want to associate with me?
[WILLIAM]
I've seen you...
...working at the Viscount
of Belfor's conservatory.
You're responsible for tending
to the gardens, is that correct?
Yeah. That's my job, all right.
[WILLIAM] Being able to
raise so many rare varieties,
it must be exceptionally
difficult.
But the results are
truly stunning.
I'm glad you like 'em.
You have a marvelous
talent, sir.
I have no doubt it would be in
demand in the Gardens of London.
[BURTON laughs]
What a load of bollocks.
My father, and
his father before him
served as gardeners
for the Viscount's family.
So, I'm destined to do the same.
We were born here and I have
no doubt that we'll die here.
There's simply no
changing that fact.
One might call it
the story of your life.
Speaking of stories,
I heard about your son.
[BURTON gasps]
[WILLIAM]
Seems your wife hasn't recovered
from her psychological trauma.
Why are you here
instead of by her side--
That's none of your business!
[CUSTOMERS murmur]
The reason I'm not there is
'cause it wouldn't do any good.
She despises me, rightfully so.
I stood by, powerless,
refusing to stand up
to the Viscount,
while my own flesh and blood
was condemned to die.
So, you mistakenly believe
that you were powerless
to save your son.
You chose to do nothing.
[BURTON gasps]
Shut up.
All right then,
what should I have done?
[BURTON]
What can I do to save Michelle?
Take vengeance.
Seems you're in luck.
You see, Mister Burton,
in addition to my teaching,
I run a consultancy
business on the side
concerning these matters.
Unless I'm mistaken,
I may be of some service to you.
[WILLIAM]
Brother.
[ALBERT]
Finished with your research?
[WILLIAM]
Yes. I found what I needed:
A way of dispelling
the darkness.
Darkness? I take it you're
referring to the Viscount?
No, not him.
I'm talking about
a perpetual gloom.
The kind that
resides in one's soul,
sapping their strength
and will to live.
[LORD BELFOR] Welcome, sirs! I
was afraid you wouldn't make it.
And miss having tea
in a literal paradise?
We wouldn't dream
of it, my lord.
Allow me to assure
you gentlemen,
it'll be everything you expected
and much, much more. Hm?
After accepting such
a generous invitation,
it'd be improper to
show up empty handed.
[LOUIS] We brought you
something quite rare.
A gift we thought
would be to your liking.
[LORD BELFOR]
Oh.
[LORD BELFOR] Ah, I'm intrigued.
Appearance wise at least,
it seems to be nothing more
than common marmalade.
Well, you should find the taste
an all-together new experience.
All right.
Such flavour.
Some variety of citrus,
but neither orange nor lemon.
Tell me.
Despite the fruit's rarity,
you wouldn't have
difficulty finding them.
They come from a plant
you're familiar with.
You don't say.
It's grapefruit, Lord Belfor.
You're joking.
This is quite a surprise.
I thought they were merely
pleasurable to look at,
but to think,
they're also delicious!
The flavour's agreeable then?
Very much so. Mm!
There's a slight
bitterness to it
which has the danger of
becoming of a new addiction.
In that case, might I
recommend the juice, as well?
It has a brisk taste
you won't find elsewhere,
particularly when
it's freshly squeezed.
Huh.
[LORD BELFOR laughs] A point
well expressed, if I do say so!
[LORD BELFOR laughs]
I had no idea this afternoon
would prove to be
so educational!
[LORD BELFOR]
Hm?
[BURTON]
Michelle! What are you doing?!
[LORD BELFOR gasps, whimpers]
[whimpers]
[MICHELLE groans]
Could someone explain to me
what the hell is going on here?!
After what you did,
you don't deserve to live!
Remember? We begged you
to help our son!
And you just let him die!
Viscount, I swear,
I'll cut out your heart
if you even have one!
[LORD BELFOR gasps]
My medicine, quick!
[WILLIAM] Worry not,
Lord Belfor. I'll retrieve it.
[LORD BELFOR groans]
[BURTON]
Here, your lordship. Drink.
Please accept my
deepest apologies.
I had no idea my wife
would do something so drastic.
[LORD BELFOR groans]
Silence!
Spare me your excuses!
You're fired, Burton!
I want you out of
my sight this instant!
But before you go,
you'll hold that woman
until the authorities arrive!
On second thought,
no need to involve the police
when I can see to a far better
punishment for her myself!
[LORD BELFOR]
The wench!
She had the gall to point
a knife at me, of all things!
But what else can you
expect from the lower class?
[ALBERT]
Please, Lord Belfor.
It isn't good for your heart
to get so worked up.
[WILLIAM] Fortunately,
she didn't cause you any harm.
Perhaps it'd be best to settle
this with them peacefully.
You actually believe
this is a matter
that can be solved peacefully?!
Oh! I swear,
that woman will pay--
Wh-What is this?
Why do I suddenly feel faint?
There's more to plants
than meets the eye.
For example, grapefruits
contain furanocoumarin,
a compound that has a profound
influence on quinine,
resulting in a sharp drop
to blood pressure.
My doctor...
Someone fetch my doctor.
- -[glass shatters]
- -[LORD BELFOR groans]
[WILLIAM] It wasn't long ago
that very same request
was made by
a distraught young couple.
[WILLIAM]
And without hesitation,
you gave them your answer.
[gasping]
Do you remember
what you told them?
[groans]
[LORD BELFOR gasps]
[LORD BELFOR]
You don't mean...
You set me up from
the very beginning?
I wondered when it would
finally dawn on you.
[MICHELLE cries]
Michelle!
You executed your role
perfectly, my darling.
[sobbing]
At Mister Burton's request,
I devised a scenario that would
appear to be a natural death.
I trusted you. How could
you do such a thing?
[WILLIAM]
This is your punishment.
For all the pain
you've inflicted,
I, William James Moriarty,
sentence you to die.
Man of your talents
should find work easily.
Might I recommend
Queen Mary's Garden?
Simply show the
letter I gave you.
I don't know how to
begin repaying you
for giving us a second chance
at life and avenging our son.
There's no need
after everything
you've been through.
The truth is,
the seed was already planted,
and while we helped
to nourish it,
in the end, its growth
and the fruits it yielded
were due to you and you alone.
[BOTH gasp]
[BURTON grunts]
[BURTON chuckles]
[LOUIS] Do you suppose
we've dispelled the darkness?
And they'll be able to carry on?
I don't see why not.
They share the
burden of a crime now--
a bond that's not
so easily broken.
[WILLIAM]
One that tethers them, eternal.
[WILLIAM] Next time
on Moriarty the Patriot  .
"The Dancers on the Bridge."